Previously on Gotham...
General Wade's
landing craft docked.
His convoy's on
the way here now.
Reunification day is today.
- Captain Gordon.
- General, welcome to Gotham.
Incoming!
Get back!
(filtered breathing)
Eduardo. What did
Walker do to you?
Eduardo's dead, Jim.
There is only Bane now.
Everything I have done here
is about punishing Gotham
for the sins of Bruce Wayne.
I'm not leaving.
And I don't think I can
let you leave... either.
What are you doing?
(grunting)
Ra's al Ghul.
This is revenge
for his death.
And who am I?
You're his daughter.
(grunting)
(shouting)
Barbara Kean.
Run!
My name is Nyssa al Ghul.
I believe you knew my father.
- Where's Nyssa?
- I don't know,
but she's planning
on using the military
to wipe out Gotham.
I can order them to stand down.
Then let's get you out of here.
This is General Wade.
Begin your bombing run
- on my order.
- Wait, wait.
(explosions in distance)
(helicopter blades whirring)
(indistinct chatter)
GORDON: We need
to get ahold of Barbara.
Nyssa al Ghul's coming for her.
The sooner she and Lee get
back here with the baby, the better.
LUCIUS: We got refugees
coming in from all over Gotham, Jim.
People are scared.
I know you're not one to quit,
but if there was ever a
time to wave the white flag,
now is it.
Nyssa al Ghul doesn't want
to just conquer Gotham...
She wants to destroy it,
kill everyone she finds.
The only thing standing between
her and these people is us.
Gather the team.
Get every able-bodied refugee
down into the bunkers
beneath the GCPD.
Why do I get the
feeling he's concocting
an elaborate plan
to get us all killed?
Better gather up these refugees.
Look at him.
The medics did everything
they could to stabilize him.
Now all we can do is wait.
This is my fault.
I sent him on this mission.
Alfred knew what he
was signing up for, Bruce.
We all did.
Nyssa and Bane are
coming after me and Barbara.
Coming after Gotham.
Because of what we did to Ra's.
What you did was stop him.
Twice.
We'll stop his psycho
daughter together.
I'm sure you
recognize this knife.
You touch my baby,
and I will turn you
into a pile of ash,
just like I did your father.
A bit cruel, don't you think?
To let this little
one get too attached
when you won't be around
much longer.
(shudders) Mmm.
(cooing)
Soon, you and Bruce Wayne
will see Gotham
and Jim Gordon's precious
Green Zone destroyed.
Then I'll allow you to die.
My father made his
name destroying empires.
Now it's my turn.
(panting) Hello.
Listen to me. There
is a submarine
in the docks, full
of Gotham's gold.
It's yours.
Just leave the city.
Let me and my baby go.
(cooing) No.
I think I'll keep
this little one
and raise her as my own.
As an al Ghul.
(laughing)
I take it the army has landed.
They're just awaiting my orders.
Then what are you waiting for?
What a cute little baby.
(indistinct chatter)
Wait, what?
You're ordering us to
destroy the Green Zone?
Anyone still in Gotham
is an enemy of the state.
I won't be party to the
murder of civilians, General.
Then you're relieved of command.
The hell are you?
(filtered breathing)
I'm your new commander.
(snap)
Does anybody else have a
problem with the general's orders?
Good.
Let's get started.
♪♪♪♪
What's the matter?
Can we really be so cavalier
about the destruction of Gotham?
(sighs) Let me think about that.
Yes!
(groans)
Damn it!
Oswald!
Where are you going?
This is my city,
and I will be damned
if I'm gonna let
those bastards take it!
I cannot let you do this.
You, of all people,
should want to
stop those monsters.
They forced you
to destroy Haven,
to murder hundreds
of innocent civilians.
You're just gonna let
'em get away with it?
I was kind of
planning on it, yeah.
Very well.
I'm going to follow my heart.
Oswald!
You have been
down this road before.
Following your heart has
never worked out for you.
Perhaps.
But perhaps you
could learn something
if you listened to this
instead of this.
I'm gonna miss you,
Edward. (crying)
I'll miss you, too, Oswald.
I'm not talking to you.
I'm talking to the...
God!
(chuckles) Come on, baby.
All right.
Okay.
Good boy.
(panting)
Go with the man in green.
(shuddering inhale)
You'll be safe.
Oswald, if you
walk off this dock,
I'm taking this submarine.
(sniffles, exhales)
And the treasure!
Nyssa al Ghul wants to
kill everyone in Gotham.
But, to get to us, the army has
to follow the Western Corridor.
That's where we make a stand.
We got a handful of men.
How are we gonna
take on an army?
We just have to slow the
army down long enough
to get General Wade out
from under Nyssa's control.
Then he can reverse
the invasion order.
We're trying to
reach the Sirens.
Still no luck.
All right. I'll go.
Jim.
I need to get Barbara
and Lee back here.
I'll meet you at the barricades.
I know you haven't seen
your kid yet, but the
GCPD needs a leader,
and they're looking to you.
I'll go to Sirens.
Okay.
(siren wailing in distance)
You sure you want to do this?
It doesn't take two of us
to track the general's signal.
And if Jim's making a stand,
that's where I should be.
Okay.
Wayne Enterprises EMP,
smoke bombs, signal jammers.
Not enough to
even the odds, but...
it may buy you some time.
What's this?
Ah. Remember the
Nightwing Project?
Portable, next-gen stealth tech.
Put it on any aircraft,
and it's invisible to radar.
But, unfortunately, it also
seems to serve as a beacon
to certain animals.
Never know.
Might find a use for it.
Oswald, come in.
(chuckles)
Still have those eyes in
the back of your head, Jim.
No. (sighs)
You just have a remarkably
recognizable odor.
Part dandy, part snake.
After all these years,
it hasn't changed.
Drink?
No, thank you.
Dulls the senses.
That's what I was going for.
Surprised you're still here.
Figured you'd be
long gone by now.
That storm you've warned
me about for so long,
it's finally here.
We've shared some
turbulent times, you and I.
That we have.
When you spared my
life on the pier that day,
banished me from Gotham,
that was the most
lost I've ever been.
(chuckles)
Because I was away
from the city, you see.
(chuckles)
It's part of me.
You know what I'm talking about,
because it's part of you, too.
(chuckles)
Sure, I could escape...
With money, I might add...
But then what?
Stand on the shores
of the mainland
and watch the army
burn it to the ground?
Then watch
tasteless industrialists
and vapid
politicians rebuild it?
(chuckles)
No.
My life is etched on
the walls of every alley
and dirty warehouse here.
My blood lives in
its broken concrete.
I'm staying to fight.
For my legacy.
BULLOCK: Hey.
The army just busted
through the GCPD checkpoint.
They're heading
to the barricades.
Bane's leading them.
How many men?
(sighs) 600, 700?
- Still want to fight?
- (gulps)
How many do we have?
Maybe 30?
(laughs)
Thirty-one.
Takes two men to pilot
that submarine, Oswald.
The dog can't do it.
(exhales)
Ditto on that blood
and concrete thing.
Kind of like this
city the way it is.
Shall we?
I believe time is
of the essence.
Gentlemen.
Remind me to talk to
you about that full pardon.
♪♪♪♪
Alvarez!
Harper, Bruce!
You take the left flank.
Harvey and I
will take the right.
Holy Mary, Mother and Joseph.
BANE: Captain Gordon...
I always knew you
had a savior complex,
but this is too much.
What happened to you, Eduardo?
There was a time when
you would have been up
on these barricades with me.
Yes... but that was before
I found my true purpose.
Stand by.
Fire on my command.
Jim, it's a lot of
innocent soldiers
down there just
following orders.
Target Bane and
Nyssa's commandos.
Fire on my command.
For Gotham.
(groans)
SELINA: Lee?
(gunfire in distance)
Selina.
Hey. Come on, we
got to get out of here.
Where's Barbara and the baby?
(exhales) Nyssa
al Ghul took them.
We have to tell Jim.
Yeah.
(gunfire continues)
The Narrows.
They never stood a chance.
The ones who could
escaped to the GCPD.
Then that's where I'm needed.
(grunts)
(grenade whistling)
- Target Jim Gordon.
- (grunts)
I'm sorry! I don't
think he can hear you
through the bullet in his ear!
(groans)
Eddie!
(screaming)
They're only
delaying the inevitable.
Jim, that thing's
pointing right at us!
(groans)
BANE: Go, go, go, go, go!
Find me Jim Gordon
and Bruce Wayne.
If the army gets
through the barricades,
they'll have a straight shot to
the GCPD and the people there.
We need to find another
way to slow them down.
I think I have a way.
GORDON: Gather all
the ammunition you can.
Fall back to the GCPD.
Go, go now!
Fall back!
We got to go. (grunts)
Well, that was a disaster.
Come on, Oswald, we
have to keep moving.
Where? There's
nowhere to hide, Jim.
Wherever we go,
the army will find us.
LUCIUS (over radio):
Get me Gordon.
It's Lucius.
Tell me you were able to
track the general's signal.
It's coming from City
Hall, but there's a problem.
Selina radioed.
Barbara and the baby were
kidnapped by Nyssa al Ghul.
General Wade's at City Hall.
Chances are Nyssa,
Barbara and the baby are, too.
Our best bet is for me to
sneak into City Hall alone.
One good electrical zap should
short out the general's chip,
then you can get him to
reverse the invasion order.
See you back at the GCPD.
Get Barbara and
the baby back safe.
Come on. Hey, move!
Upsy-daisy, Oswald.
(Oswald grunting)
We're running out of time.
(gasps) Just give me one minute.
I'm so sorry.
I saw the grenade
and I froze. (exhales)
I'm sor... Shh.
It's the least I could do.
But tell me...
Does it look bad?
No, it's just a scr... (gags)
Looks fine. Let's go.
Where'd everybody go?
She's gonna need some morphine.
(explosion)
And this bandage needs changing.
Lee.
Bruce. Is Jim...?
He's okay. For now.
We'll need to get Jeremiah's
battery from the basement.
After the bridges went
down, Lucius re-modified
Jeremiah's bomb to be
used for its original purpose...
as a battery.
It's been powering the GCPD.
Right.
We need to make it a bomb again.
You got to be kidding me.
Jeremiah knew exactly
where to put his bombs
to topple buildings,
turn Gotham into a maze.
We stopped him.
But if we could use
just part of his plan,
we can trap the army
and slow them down.
By knocking buildings
down like dominos.
But for that to work, we need
to put a bomb in this building.
Ground Zero for the blast.
Wayne Enterprises.
Bruce...
There's no other way.
Okay. How do we get
this thing out of here?
To use it as a bomb, you
don't need the whole thing.
All you need is... the core...
and the activator.
(electricity powering down)
That's it?
It may look modest,
but all it took was one of these
to blow up an entire bridge.
Not to mention the
Gotham Clock Tower.
Bruce, you can't do this alone.
He's not alone.
I know where to place the bomb.
And you and Lucius
are needed here.
I can't believe we're
letting them do this.
Add that to the list
of things that I cannot
believe are happening.
Hey.
What?
(grunting)
(snap)
BARBARA: The key's there.
Where is she? Is she okay?
Yeah, she's
upstairs in the office
with Nyssa and the general.
Nyssa is not gonna stop until
she's killed everyone in Gotham.
One thing at a time,
let's go save our baby.
NYSSA: Hello, Captain Gordon.
(guns cocking)
Ah.
You're seeing your
baby for the first time.
(sighs)
I wish I had a camera.
Hand her over.
No.
I don't think I will.
Put down your guns.
Unless you want the little
one hurt in the crossfire.
(chuckles)
Even now, the army is making
its way to the Green Zone
while Bane is hunting
down Bruce Wayne.
Only question is,
what to do with you?
This is it.
The bomb will weaken
the support column
and topple the entire building.
This is crazy.
I mean, we've spent this entire
time trying to stop Jeremiah
and now we're actually
using part of his plan.
Believe me...
if there was any other way...
SELINA: You sure
you want to do this?
First Wayne Manor gets destroyed
and now Wayne Enterprises.
This building is the heart
of my family's company.
There are things above us
my parents spent
their entire lives on.
Some of my earliest memories
are playing with
Alfred in this lobby,
waiting for my parents to
come down these escalators.
But my parents
built this company
to make Gotham a better place.
They would have sacrificed
everything for this city.
They did sacrifice everything.
And if that's what it takes...
so will I.
(exhales)
SELINA: So remind
me how this works.
Pulls energy from
the air and magnifies it.
And when it does that?
We run!
(clamoring)
(screaming)
♪♪♪♪
I knew you'd
come for your child.
I just didn't think
you'd be foolish enough
to come alone.
I don't need help
to take you down.
Don't you see?
It's over.
Gotham will burn.
And I'll achieve what
my father couldn't.
Including killing you.
(chuckles)
She likes to be held upright.
(baby cooing) There.
Barbara, I'll deal with you once
Gotham has been destroyed.
But I'd like you to see this.
(both grunting)
I was expecting
a little more gusto.
You want gusto?
(both grunt)
Is that all you got?
(radio beeping)
It's Lieutenant Angel.
They did what?
No, no.
Is there another way around?
Then tell the army
to blast through.
GORDON: Hey.
I'm not done with you yet.
Your friends may have
bought you some time,
but the Green Zone's
destruction is only delayed.
And now to meet your fate.
(handcuffs close)
Let's meet it together.
(grunting)
Barbara!
(Gordon screams)
(gunfire)
Shoot him.
No.
(grunting)
You think you can defeat me?
Better men and women
have tried and failed.
(grunting)
(shouts)
I'm an al Ghul.
You'll never beat me; I have
my father's blood in my veins.
I am his one true heir.
Do you ever stop talking?
(cries out)
You two do share one thing.
You both love getting
stabbed by this knife.
General Wade.
Execute fail-safe.
No.
I'm going to enjoy watching
Gotham be destroyed!
And then my legacy
will be complete.
We got to hurry.
It's only a matter of time
before the army breaks through.
We need to get back to the GCPD.
- (grunts)
- Bruce!
Impressive. You blew
up your father's building
to stop the military.
It will take more to stop me.
Go on ahead, Selina!
Warn the GCPD!
No, we're doing this together.
You shouldn't have hurt Alfred.
Collateral damage.
It happens in war.
I'm sorry you weren't there
to see me break your butler,
but I'm so glad you won't
miss me killing your little friend.
Let her go.
In war, there are
no attachments.
Only then can you fight
without your hands tied.
You see... just a little
ounce of pressure.
That's all that separates
the living from the dead.
(shouts) (cries out)
(device beeping)
SELINA: What is that?
BRUCE: Wayne cloaking
device, but it had some glitches.
Apparently, it's a beacon
for certain winged mammals.
SELINA: What winged mammals?
(wings flapping)
(squealing)
Bats.
(pained grunting)
There's no way to
reverse the invasion order.
We have to find another way.
- Is she all right?
- She is now.
There, there. Mama's
here. (baby cooing)
And your father.
Try not to get blood on her.
Sir...
- (rasping): Come on.
We're almost at the Green Zone.
(mask whirring and clicking)
(hisses)
(breathing steadily)
Lee?
Jim.
The baby? I checked
her over, she's fine.
Though she could use a feed.
(baby cooing)
Where's General Wade?
The army's broken through.
General Wade's dead.
Nyssa al Ghul
escaped. There's no way
to order the army to stand down.
So, now what?
The army blew up
Wayne Enterprises
and knocked down
two other buildings.
We don't stand a chance.
Actually, that was
Bruce and Selina.
What?
The army's blocks away.
GORDON: From what
direction? Every direction.
We're surrounded.
Jim. I need to get
her out of here.
All right. The tunnels
underneath the GCPD.
There's a vent shaft, it
connects to the subway line.
Take the baby and the
refugees down into the subways.
Get 'em behind enemy lines.
- Don't stop till
you get to safety.
- Okay.
But what about you?
We'll hold 'em off outside,
buy you some time.
- Jim...
- These refugees,
most of them are
from the Narrows.
They know you, they trust you.
They know you'll protect them.
Go.
Oh, there you are, Master Bruce.
Rest, Alfred.
All this time, I
tried to protect you.
Here you are, a soldier.
A soldier for good.
You've spent your
life protecting me.
Now it's time for
me to do the same.
It's time for me
to protect Gotham.
Even if there's
nothing left to defend.
All right, everyone,
let's move. Okay.
All right, you'll walk about
five blocks underground,
and then you'll get
to a subway vent. Go.
You're not coming with us?
Jim and our friends are
out there making a stand.
That's where I belong.
Wait, what are we
going to do without you?
Survive. Make sure
this was all worth it. Go.
What was that for?
Everything you've done for me.
And for her.
Just get them to safety.
It's over, Jim.
Our war's come to an end.
This isn't a war.
This is a firing squad.
I told you to go.
And I didn't listen.
Ready.
(panting)
Aim.
(rifles cocking)
MAN: Shoulder to shoulder.
- Stand together.
- What the...?
They're here for us, Jim.
Fire.
(crowd quiets)
I said fire!
GORDON: You have a choice.
You can stand with us, or
you can stand with them.
(crowd cheering)
CROWD (chanting): We are Gotham!
We are Gotham! We are Gotham!
(coughing)
So that bitch was
telling the truth after all.
(dog barking)
LUCIUS: We managed to
raise the mainland on the radio.
They know everything.
As of right now,
the army's being repurposed
for the humanitarian
mission of rebuilding Gotham.
These refugees will get
food, water, medical treatment.
They're setting up a crisis
center in Federal Square.
I'll be damned.
Hey.
So...
this whole "not
listening" thing.
It's not gonna
become a habit, is it?
You're welcome.
Go.
(chuckles softly)
Well, this is gonna make
one hell of a bedtime
story some day.
Can I?
Of course.
I don't even know
what to call her.
Barbara.
Oh.
Barbara Lee Gordon.
In this city, it's important
she know who she can rely on.
(cooing)
Bruce, what's wrong?
We won.
Nyssa al Ghul
is still out there.
And she and Bane were right.
All this happened because of me,
because people
were trying to hurt me
and the people I care about.
When Bane had you...
I thought he was
gonna kill you, Selina,
and there was
nothing I could do.
Hey.
I will be here
whenever you need me.
What?
That's what my
parents used to tell me.
Come here.
That bitch stole our submarine!
And our gold.
And by now she's probably landed
somewhere on the
mainland, impossible to track!
After all we've been
through these last months,
we are once again
left with nothing!
Nothing!
(grunts)
Back to square one.
Common criminals.
We saved this city
from certain damnation,
but will we see any
credit for our loyalty,
our selfless bravery?
Of course not!
I don't want their thanks.
(panting)
Or their respect.
You know what I felt,
standing shoulder to shoulder
with those people out there?
Nothing.
I...
feel...
absolutely nothing
for those drab...
boring people.
That was me once.
Minimum wage at a thankless job
at the GCPD.
"Yes, sir. No, sir.
Thank you so much, sir."
Picking up scraps
from my master's floor.
Shy, awkward...
pathetic Ed.
Common criminals?
Never again.
I've shown this city who
I truly am once before,
and I will do it again.
They will bow
to the Riddler, and
they won't get up
until I permit them to.
Yes.
You're right.
Our accomplishments
have been erased,
our brilliant minds underrated.
If they had let me run this
city the way I wanted to,
it would not be in ruins now.
I have the men, the money,
- the guns...
- Gordon took them.
Why? Because he still sees you
as Fish Mooney's umbrella
boy, and he always will.
Yes.
I only came back to
help him save this city
so that I could
take it for myself.
We would be stronger together.
No one could stop us.
Yeah, perhaps.
Let's make a pact,
here and now.
We will take what we want
from who we want,
and we will suffer no fools.
Together.
Shall we shake on that?
Please,
we're brothers.
A hug.
A hug it is.
(panting)
(sighs)
Life begins anew.
Shall we get to work?
MAN: Thank you all
for coming here today.
It is my great honor to
introduce Mayor Chang.
(crowd murmuring)
CHANG: With
reunification underway
and the bridges being rebuilt,
it is my honor to bestow
upon Captain James Gordon
the title of commissioner.
(applause)
(indistinct chatter)
We're gonna miss
you around the bullpen.
I won't be far.
And the mission doesn't change.
Still trying to make
this city a better place.
Be careful.
You're swimming with sharks now.
If you need anything, ever...
I know who to call.
You deserve this, Jim.
You really do.
I'm gonna go get
a drink before...
you get all teary-eyed on me.
(sniffles)
What do you mean,
you're leaving?
Bane's in prison, it's over.
My life here... it's too public.
You've made up your mind.
Gotham's in good hands.
Commissioner.
Yeah.
Thank you, Bruce,
for everything you've
done for me and for the city.
Gotham will always be your home.
Bruce is all grown up.
- That he is.
- Well,
now you have another
little one to look after.
Where's Bruce?
Um...
he left you this.
(shuddering)
BRUCE: You know how to
reach me if you need anything?
Yes.
Well, you know me, Master
Bruce, I'll be very self-sufficient.
Busy, actually. You know,
we start the reconstruction
of Wayne Enterprises and
Wayne Manor tomorrow.
You will remember everything
I taught you, won't you?
Of course.
Good, that's... that's good.
I never tried to replace
your parents, you know?
I couldn't, I never would.
But I want you to
know, Master Bruce,
that you are the only son
that I will ever have,
and I could not be more proud.
(shuddering)
(turbine whirring)
(airplane taking off)
♪♪♪♪